{"tossups": [{"question": "This man was a named an All-American while playing lacrosse for Syracuse, though he chose to pursue football professionally; he currently holds the longest-standing franchise record for rushing yards. This running back starred in <em>Ice Station Zebra</em> and <em>The Dirty Dozen</em> after unexpectedly retiring from the NFL in 1966. For the point, name this Hall of Fame football player for Cleveland, whose career rushing mark was first broken by Walter Payton.", "answer": "Jim <b><u>Brown</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Bruno Latour discussed the role of \"contingency\" and \"black boxes\" in this field in a book analyzing it \"in action.\" This field was analyzed in terms of periods of \"normal\" \"puzzle-solving\" activity interrupted by drastic \"paradigm shifts\" in Thomas Kuhn's book on the structure of its revolutions. For the point, name this field whose falsificationist approach was developed by Karl Popper and whose \"method,\" outlined by Francis Bacon, involves hypothesis and experiment.", "answer": "<b><u>science</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Sociology"}, {"question": "This author used the Port Jervis lynching of 1892 as the basis for his short story about the disfigurement of Henry Johnson, \"The Monster.\" He chronicled the effects of alcoholism and poverty on Irish immigrants, including a protagonist who is killed after becoming a prostitute, in <em>Maggie: A Girl of the Streets</em>. For the point, name this American author who wrote about Jim Conklin receiving the title Civil War wound in <em>The Red Badge of Courage.</em>", "answer": "Stephen <b><u>Crane</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "A participating force in this war rented sixty coal vessels from a German cruise line in order to complete their journey to battle. This war almost expanded to include Britain after the Dogger Bank incident. This war ended dramatically when the Baltic Fleet sailed more than halfway around the world to meet its doom at Tsushima Straits. For the point, name this war which ended in 1905 with a European power shocked at losing to an ascendant Asian empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Russo-Japanese</u></b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The 1979 Herb Alpert song \"Rise\" was sampled behind this man's song \"Hypnotize,\" and he lamented that \"It's like the more money we come across, the more problems we see\" in another hit. Following this man's 1997 murder in Los Angeles, his associate Sean Combs reworked a Police song into the tribute \"We'll Be Missing You.\" For the point, name this rival of Tupac Shakur, a rapper who took on a stage name referencing his girth.", "answer": "The <b><u>Notorious B.I.G.</u></b> [or Christopher George Latore <b><u>Wallace</u></b>; or <b><u>Biggie</u></b> Smalls]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This man embroiled his country in the disastrous Livonian War, and he commissioned the construction of St. Basil's Cathedral to commemorate his victory over Kazan. This man is depicted in an Ilya Repin painting just realizing that he has killed his son with a flagpole. He was the first Prince of Muscovy (<b>pr. MUSK-oh-vee</b>) to take the title \"tsar of Russia.\" For the point, name this member of the Rurikid Dynasty who was known for his savagery.", "answer": "<b><u>Ivan the Terrible</u></b> [or <b><u>Ivan Grozny</u></b>; or <b><u>Ivan IV</u></b>; prompt on <b><u>Ivan</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The image of George Harris placing flowers into rifle barrels was taken at this building. Clarence Renshaw was instructed to revise the design of this building to double the number of restrooms, though Franklin Roosevelt, on a tour, forbade using the new capacity for the intended purpose of racial segregation. This building was hit by American Airlines Flight 77 in September 2001. For the point, identify this headquarters of the U.S. Department of Defense.", "answer": "The <b><u>Pentagon</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1981, a building of this kind was destroyed in Operation Opera, an Israeli mission that followed up on the Iranian Scorch Sword project. That Iraqi example of this kind of facility was located as Osirak. The 2010 Stuxnet worm disabled facilities of this kind while currently, Bushehr (<b>pr.boo-SHARE</b>) is a building of this kind supplied with Russian materials in Iran. For the point, name these facilities that contain centrifuges and provide power or weapons.", "answer": "<b><u>nuclear reactor</u></b>s [or <b><u>uranium enrichment</u></b> facilities; or <b><u>nuclear</u></b> power <b><u>plants</u></b>]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This country was the first to invoke the Eisenhower Doctrine, asking U.S. marines to land here at the invitation of president Camille Chamoun. In 1983, this country was the site of the deadliest day in U.S. military history since the Tet Offensive, when a Marine barracks was blown up by a Shiite militia. For the point, name this country where the U.S. largely stayed out of a protracted civil war in the 1980s following that attack in Beirut.", "answer": "<b><u>Lebanon</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This party's initial financial backers included U.S. Steel magnate Frank Munsey. It was chaired by Hiram Johnson, who became its Vice-Presidential candidate. This party got its name following John Schrank's attempted assassination of its Presidential nominee, who announced that he was \"as fit as\" a large animal despite the shooting. For the point, name this party that finished second in the 1912 Presidential election behind ex-President Theodore Roosevelt.", "answer": "<b><u>Bull Moose</u></b> party [or the <b><u>1912 Progressive</u></b> Party until \"1912\" is read; prompt on <b><u>Progressive</u></b> Party]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man was targeted by the Ruthven Raid, which briefly imprisoned him. He denounced smoking in his pamphlet <em>A Counterblast to Tobacco</em> and advocated the divine right of kings in <em>The True Law of Free Monarchies</em>. As great-grandson of Margaret Tudor, he earned the right to rule on the death of Elizabeth I. For the point, name this king who began the Jacobean era and united the crowns of Scotland and England in 1603.", "answer": "<b><u>James I</u></b> [or <b><u>James VI</u></b> of Scotland; prompt on <b><u>James</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This painter provided a visual record of the dress of the Schlachta (<b>pr. shlak-TAH</b>) class in his <em>A Polish Nobleman</em>. A 1990 burglary at Boston's Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum targeted this man's painting <em>Storm on the Sea of Galilee</em>, which remains missing. In 1632, this Dutch painter depicted a medical school class conducted by Nicholas Tulp. For the point, name this painter of <em>Return of the Prodigal Son</em> and <em>The Night Watch</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Rembrandt</u></b> Harmenszoon van Rijn", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This man's initial campaign slogan \"in your heart, you know he's right\" was mocked by his opponent, who claimed \"in your guts, you know he's nuts.\" This man was also targeted with the Daisy ad, which criticized his seeming plan to turn the Vietnam War into a nuclear conflict. He lends his name to a conservative wing of the Republican Party which was ascendant under Ronald Reagan. For the point, name this losing 1964 Presidential candidate.", "answer": "Barry <b><u>Goldwater</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A movement to eliminate corruption in these places was led by Odo and known as the Cluniac reform. These facilities were subject to the Benedictine Rule and were governed by officials such as priors and abbots. For the point, name these places that could belong to Dominican, Augustinian, or Cistercian orders and were where Christian religious specialists lived in the Middle Ages.", "answer": "<b><u>monasteries</u></b> [or <b><u>nunneries</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This area was first systematically explored in 1869 by the Cook\u2013Folsom\u2013Peterson Expedition, though it was William Henry Jackson's photographs, taken as part of the Hayden Geological Survey, that spurred Ulysses Grant to sign the Act of Dedication in 1872, legally designating this place. For the point, name this first U.S. National Park, found mostly in Wyoming.", "answer": "<b><u>Yellowstone</u></b> National Park", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man issued a proclamation of religious tolerance alongside Licinius. This man married Fausta, the sister of Maxentius, following a victory that occurred when he dreamed of the words \"in this sign you shall conquer\" and a flaming cross. This victor at Milvian Bridge ordered the renovation of Byzantium into a new capital and issued the Edict of Milan. For the point, name this first Roman emperor to convert to Christianity.", "answer": "<b><u>Constantine I</u></b> [or <b><u>Constantine</u></b> the Great]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "A musical about people who do this action includes the songs \"Unworthy of Your Love\" and \"Everybody's Got the Right.\" A plan to perform this action is at the center of Giuseppe Verdi's opera <em>A Masked Ball</em>, which had to move its setting from Sweden to Boston to avoid controversy over depicting this action. For the point, name this action which Gustav III suffers in the opera and is done in a Stephen Sondheim show to Abraham Lincoln and John F. Kennedy.", "answer": "<b><u>assassination</u></b> [or word forms; or <b><u>killing</u></b>, <b><u>murder,</u></b> etc.]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "Supporters of this man wore hemlock in their hair and included men such as Jason Parmenter, who were subject to mock executions. This man was opposed by Benjamin Lincoln at the orders of governor James Bowdoin. His goal was to seize the Springfield arsenal and forcibly erase debts. For the point, name this Massachusetts insurgent whose actions showed the weaknesses of the post-independent American government, in his namesake \"rebellion.\"", "answer": "Daniel <b><u>Shays</u></b> (make sure they say \u201cShays\u201d and not \u201cShay\u201d which is incorrect)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Eduard Hitzig and Gustav Fritsch showed how this organ can be stimulated to function by electricity. An accidental case study on this organ occurred in 1848, when an explosion drove an iron rod through the one belonging to Phineas Gage. Paul Broca and Carl Wernicke <b>(pr. VUR-nick-uh</b>) studied the role of this organ in speech. For the point, name this organ which was subject to Walter Freeman and Ant\u00f3nio Moniz's liberal use of the lobotomy procedure.", "answer": "human <b><u>brain</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {"question": "Inhabitants of this island worshipped the mysterious \"snake goddess\" and had their trade curtailed by the eruption of Thera. This island was decorated with \"bull-leaping\" frescoes and was where the legendary Minotaur's labyrinth was located. This island was the home to a writing system deciphered by Michael Ventris, Linear B. For the point, name this origin of the Minoan civilization, a large island that contained an ancestral Greek culture.", "answer": "<b><u>Crete</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Stamata Revithi unofficially participated in this event, which formally barred women. Carl Schuhmann was a big winner at this event, whose focal point was a marathon won by Spyridon Louis. This event was the brainchild of Pierre de Coubertin and took place in Athens in 1896. For the point, identify this festival which re-introduced an ancient athletic tradition to the modern world and is now held every four years.", "answer": "first Summer <b><u>Olympics</u></b> [or 1896 Summer <b><u>Olympics</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Daniel Colladon determined this value in water in order to perform further research on compressibility. This value for air was first measured by Pierre Gassendi in an experment involving a muzzle flash. The first person to travel in a controlled fashion faster than this value was Chuck Yeager, who broke a namesake \"barrier\" by achieving Mach 1 in 1947. For the point, name this value equal to about 343 meters per second.", "answer": "<b><u>speed of sound</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "This national leader presided over the \"Special Period\" beginning in 1991. As a younger man, this man formed the 26th of July Movement following his \"History Will Absolve Me\" speech during a trial for attacking the Moncada Barracks. This man disembarked from the <em>Granma</em> alongside Che Guevara during his successful second attempt at overthrowing Fulgencio Batista. For the point, name this dictator who ruled from 1959 to 2008 in Cuba.", "answer": "<b><u>F</u></b>idel <b><u>Castro</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>Castro</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man engineered the Convention of Gastein, which added Schleswig and Holstein to his country's territory at the expense of Denmark. This editor of the Ems Dispatch claimed the \"blood and iron\" would solve the questions of his day, and had a troubled relationship with Wilhelm II that led to his removal from office in 1890. For the point, name this diplomat who sparked the Franco-Prussian War as the final phase of his plan for German unification.", "answer": "Otto von <b><u>Bismarck</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This office was at the head of the \"tent government\" and originated as the \"barbarian-quelling generalissimo.\" Holders of this title established the Kamakura and Ashikaga eras. For the point, name this office which wielded actual power for most of the recorded history of Japan, in the name of the figurehead emperor.", "answer": "<b><u>shogun</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Prior to becoming Prime Minster of France, Georges Clemenceau (clem-en-SO) operated one of these institutions called <em>L'Aurore</em>. Jules Streicher was hanged at Nuremberg for running one of these things known as <em>Der St\u00fcrmer</em> (<b>pr. SHTUR-mur</b>). British politics were influenced by <em>The</em> <em>Guardian</em>, <em>The Evening Standard</em>, and other examples of these things in broadsheet or tabloid format. For the point, identify these things that include the <em>Times</em> of London.", "answer": "<b><u>newspaper</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The term \"barracks\" is used to disparage military men who seized this position during the Crisis of the Third Century. Nerva began an era of these people known as the \"Five Good\" ones, while Otho and Vindex were among the lesser lights during the \"year of the four\" of these people. For the point, name this office held by men such as Tiberius and Claudius.", "answer": "<b><u>Roman emperor</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>emperor</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man was dispatched to Finland Station in a \"sealed train\" by mischievous Germans, who believed that his presence would unsettle his home country. There, he issued the April Theses and wrote <em>What Is to Be Done?</em>, which put him in position to take leadership of the October Revolution following eight months of the Provisional Government. For the point, name this leader of the Bolsheviks who became the founder of the Soviet Union.", "answer": "Vladimir <b><u>Lenin</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This country hosted an arms reduction summit that included the \"double-zero\" proposal and led to the signing of 1987's Intermediate-Range Nuclear Forces Treaty. This country fought the bloodless Cod War with the United Kingdom, and its Althing declared its total independence from Denmark in 1944. For the point, name this Scandinavian country whose volcanic eruptions sometimes cause chaos in the international air travel system.", "answer": "<b><u>Iceland</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During this war, stylized propaganda posters reminded citizens that \"loose lips sink ships.\" People on the home front of this war were encouraged to plant \"victory gardens,\" and many women went to work in factories during this war, following the example of \"Rosie the Riveter.\" For the point, name this war in which Americans mobilized to defeat the Axis.", "answer": "<b><u>World War II</u></b> <b>Extra (ONLY READ IF YOU BOTCH A QUESTION!)</b> The Nazi government awarded the \"Mutterkreuz\" to people who performed this action at least ten times. In Fascist Italy, a \"Battle for\" this action was declared. Since 1979, this action has been limited to once for the majority of women in China. For the point, name this action which Romania sought to promote by banning abortion and earned Soviets the Mothers' Medal.  ANSWER: giving <b><u>birth</u></b> [or equivalents]", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}